We started this a little bit a little bit last time. We're just going to do a little bit of a recap and then okay. So let me open up here. Okay. Hold on hold on. Now recording I'm not even talking. All right. So we had started
we ended two weeks ago with a discussion about washing dishes and it's a very relevant thing. We're going to try to cover some ground tonight to get into issues of washing dishes. We're going to hopefully see how much we get to the next big topic, the topic of Not Bar Not, the topic of Nosein Ta'am LiFgam. But we'll see how much we get through tonight. Okay so if you remember if you go to the Shulchan Aruch in Sif Gimmel, Tzadi Hei Gimmel, Tzadi Hei Gimmel. So we mentioned the Shulchan Aruch mentions, which we saw that,
well let's start let's take one step back. Source 38 again we did this last year just to go briefly. Source 38 is the Tur. Okay? The Tur quotes a Sefer HaTrumah. Sefer HaTrumah says if you accidentally rinsed, back now we we we washed we took a big pot and that's how we wash dishes in it. So the Sefer HaTrumah is quoted in the Tur by saying if you accidentally rinse a clean dairy Ben Yomo utensil, that means I used a fork earlier for macaroni and cheese, okay? And I then clean it in a Fleishig Ben
Yomo pot, okay? Which is on the fire or off the fire but it's still hot, everything is assur. The pot is assur, why? Because it has Milchigs in it. The fork is assur, why? That fork's a Kli Sheini though, right? Are we assuming it's not? Let's assume it's not, let's assume it's a what I mean yeah well let's assume it touched something hot, was used that day. So everything's going to be assur. That that is the Tur. The Rosh in source 38, the Rosh quoted by the Tur quotes his father, but the other way: even
if I have dairy utensils and Fleishig utensils and they're both Ben Yomo, everything is going to be muttar so long as they are clean. If they're dirty, then it's going to create a problem. The Shulchan Aruch paskens this way in source in sorry in Sif Gimmel like the Rosh. כקערות של בשר שהודחו ביורה חולבת if I clean a meat plate that I washed in a Milchig pot, it was Yad
Soledes Bo and even if they're both Ben Yuman muttar. I'm going to share later by the way some one of the Semichas Chaver here somebody created a pretty cool AI stuff to figure out all these different things so I'll share that later with everybody. מותר משום דהוה ליה נותן טעם בר נותן טעם דהתירא this is Not Bar Not. Okay. Why is it Not Bar Not? Because I was Nosein Ta'am from my macaroni and cheese into my fork.
The fork is now Nosein Ta'am into the water and now that's Not Bar Not Deheiteira and therefore everything is going to be muttar like the Rosh says, unless something is very very dirty. The Shulchan Aruch continues and says שאמר ברור לי שלא היה שומן hold on hold on I only get through a bunch and then we can hold on shedavuk bahen ואם היה שומן דבוק בהן but if it was really dirty, צריך שיהיה במים ששים כנגד ממשות שומן שעל הקערה. Okay, fine.
The Rama - yeah? The assumption is that the water in that pot is not all that hot otherwise you wouldn't be able to- it says Yad Soledes Bo. It says Yad Soledes Bo. Even if it's hot. It says it. Yad Soledes Bo. Yeah that's the chiddush. If it's not Yad Soledes Bo then it's definitely not an issue. The chiddush is if it's Yad Soledes Bo but it's still Not Bar Not. If you wash them all in cold water nothing's going to be a problem. Okay the Rama paskens not like the Sefer- not like the Rosh but paskens like the
Sefer HaTrumah. Once again, Ashkenazim we are more machmir. Okay? ויש אוסרים אפילו אין שומן דבוק בהן says the Rama, no. Even if they're- they're- אלא אם כן אחד מן הכלים אינן בני יומן says the Rama, if one of them is not Ben Yomo. Blias Kli Rishon. The Rama we'll come back to the Rama in a second that if both utensils are Ben Yomo it's going to be a problem.
If there is a big Taz here, there's actually a few big Tazes, but this Taz in Sif Katan Ches on the previous page where the Taz explains and paskens like the Sefer HaTrumah like the Rama explain- he explains the Rama that Not Bar Not is bedieved. Not Bar Not is bedieved. And this he explains potentially is worse than Not Bar Not. This would be worse than Not Bar Not. That that is. That is the Taz, I'm sorry, in סעיף קטן כ\"ח.
If you look, you're not going to do over Shavuos, you should look at this Taz. He explains two things. He says, number one, what you're concerned that the utensils are touching each other. If they're touching each other, that's not nat bar nat, that is nosein ta'am, that's a problem. That's number one potentially. And secondly, even if it's not nat bar nat, even if not nat bar nat, I know it's very confusing. He adds one more piece and he says,
it's one thing when I made macaroni and cheese, and then I cleaned the pot, and then I made something else, okay, so nosein ta'am one, nosein ta'am second time. Here, it's happening immediately. You're putting everything in hot water at the same time. Nothing's weakened, everything is still rumbling around, it's still boiling water, so potentially it's more of an issue and that's why the Rama paskins like the Sefer HaTrumah to say no, this is not a case of nat bar nat. Nat bar nat assumes there is a weakening of flavor.
Why is there a weakening of flavor? Number one, I'm worried that things are touching each other, okay? Even the utensils are shomer negiah. And second of all, that it's nothing's weakened, it's all happening in real time. It's not like I made something three hours earlier and now I'm making something later, so okay, it's weakened, it's in the walls of the pot. It's happening right now. I have a milchig fork, I have a fleishig pot, it's all happening at the same time. So if you look, what if there's detergent in... one second, one second, give me a minute Eddie, you're going to wrap up the shiur at this
point. Hold up. Go to source thirty-nine. So source thirty-nine, the שאלות ותשובות השיב שלמה explains that הפירוש השני אף הטעם השני המעורב במים, that the second reason, right, that when the fleishig flavor leaves the utensil, which is what we're talking about, okay? That it immediately meets the dairy flavor, right? I have my milchig fork in this pot. They meet, it's love at first sight. There isn't like we're getting to know each other, we're going out
for a while, they're meeting each other right away. That was a very good mashal by the way, I just want to point out. That was not in the notes by the way, I'm just going to share that. Pretty probably shouldn't be. Okay. So he explains the following. He says, הטעם השני המעורב במים אינו קלוש, it's not weakened, ובתנאי שמחובר למקור הטעם, it's all there together, היינו שנמצא בקדירה שפולטת כל הזמן טעמה למים. It's spitting out the flavor. על כן אוסר בהתפגשו עם טעם השני אחר שבתוך
המים אף על גב שמתערב במים. I don't care that it's mixing around, it's all meeting each other at the same time, and therefore the Rama is machmir like the Sefer HaTrumah not just to be machmir to be machmir sake. This is not a case of נותן טעם בר נותן טעם because there is too many other factors that are involved. Okay, if you look, we're not going to, if you look in the Shach in סעיף קטן י\"ב, it's a small Shach, but the Shach says, right there on the right side, vetaima the Shach explains כשהטעם השני של בשר ושל חלב נכנסים במים מיד נאסר המים.
He explains that when everything is happening together the water becomes assur וחוזר ואוסר הקערות והיורה. אבל כשאחד מהם הקערות או היורה אינו בן יומו כל הכלים מותרים. So if it's not eino ben yomo, it's not going to be a problem, but he says when I throw it all in, I have a fleishig pot, throw everything in the pot together, now it's all mixed around, the water becomes assur, and therefore it becomes a big, big, big problem. Okay. Go back to the Rama now. Okay, the Rama just to go through this quickly, the Rama now adds like many, many
halachos, adds seven different halachos, we're going to run through them quickly, I'm not going to spend that much time on them, but it's worth just to go through them so that we can move on. Okay, va'teir in the Rama. So the Rama says, yes, אבל אם שניהם בני יומן, if they are both bnei yoman, והדיח אותן ביחד בכלי ראשון, and what do I do? And either plate is, oh sorry,
בני יומן והודחו בכלי ראשון, yeah, okay, if they're both bnei yoman and you wash them together b'kli rishon, הכל אסור והכי נוהגין ואין לשנות. Okay, so that's pretty clear. ודווקא כשהודחו ביחד ובכלי ראשון. That's only when I wash them in a kli rishon, והודחו זה אחר זה. If I have a big, big pot, but I want one after the other, או b'kli sheini אפילו ביחד הכל שרי. Okay, so number one or number two
really, if I'm going to wash, if they are washed one after the other, or the pot is actually kli sheini, it's not going to be a problem. Why? Because then it's really weakened, then it actually is, that's the Rama's point, now you're really talking that something is weakened. Fine. If the fork is dirty and you're cleaning it, it must be dirty. Well, it depends what dirty means, meaning if there's processed or stuff on the... No, no, if there's mamashus on it then we're going to be more concerned. Right. Right. So you're not washing off the macaroni cheese off
it. Correct, correct, correct. In that would be the case then you would need shishim. Then you would need shishim. Right, right. Okay, then he goes further and he says, ve'im irah miklee... Ah, okay. So now now now we get to a concept called iruy. Water is running... yeah, hold on. We should do this Taz or not? No. Okay. ואם עירה מכלי ראשון של בשר על כלי חלב.
Though this is a concept called iruy. What is iruy? It's running water. Where I pour water. So I take water, I pour hot cooked water from a אינו בן יומו פליישיג pot. So I take a אינו בן יומו פליישיג pot and I pour hot water directly onto something that is milchig. So says the Rema, דינו ככלי ראשון ואוסר אם היה בן יומו. There is a concept
called iruy. iruy means uninterrupted stream. Where do we find this concept usually? We find this in hilchos Shabbos, okay? This is why when you make tea on Shabbos, okay, assuming that you hold of klee shlishi when it comes to tea on Shabbos, so when you make tea, the urn is your klee rishon, your cup is your klee sheini, your second cup is your klee shlishi, but you can't put the tea bag into the third cup, well, second cup. You said in the second cup. Second cup. Because when the water goes directly on
it, that's called iruy miklee sheini and whatever the wherever the stream is coming from, it has the status of that klee. Okay, so fine. We find this in we find this also in Pesach when it comes to koshering countertops. Person is can't like keep on the like doing this and doing this and doing this. It's got to be one interrupted stream to kosher everything because otherwise if it's you know if it's if it's if it's interrupted then it doesn't have the status of a klee rishon and it's a problem. So if I take something and I pour directly on it, wherever the stream is coming from, that is considered the klee itself.
Okay, the the Taz in סעיף קטן י\"ג. Yeah, the Taz just explains that since it's an uninterrupted stream, it's the the uninterrupted stream of water is not really is not in the concept of nat bar nat because it's uninterrupted and therefore it maintains everything. Okay, there is a Shach... again, we can go through these quickly, but the Shach in סעיף קטן
י\"ח says that if you look, this is a very, very small Shach, it's an important Shach because it quotes the Pri Megadim in which the Shach says only the bottom plate is going to be really assur because the dairy, you know, this heat doesn't just like keep traveling up, wherever the water hits will be a problem. Okay, fine. I'm going to skip some of these because I I don't think it's as exciting. Fine. Okay, just go to source forty in the booklets. This is the Chachmas Adam and
then we can move on. The Chachmas Adam says the following. Chachmas Adam... Okay. Chachmas Adam says the following. It says אם עירה מים מכלי של בשר נקי. If I poured from a fleishig pot that was ben yomo, clean. I mean bo zman this morning it's cleaned out. And I pour water from there על של חלב בן יומו. midino mutar legamri. So so he says lemaiseh
we're pretty lenient. So he says, skip to afilu minhageinu le'asar, even though today we might assur כששתי הפליטות מסתערבין יחד, when like you have, you know, different things get mixed up, אבל לא שייך בעירוי דהא הוי נותן בר נותן מכל מקום מקום שאין הפסד יש לאסור דחשבינן ליה כלו ניצוק המקלח מכלי לכלי מחבר יחד שתי הפליטות. So lemaiseh we are pretty machmir about this unless it's a real case of a hefsed. So if I had a ben yomo fleishig
pot of and I poured water I took water and I pour that onto a ben yomo dairy pot, that would potentially assur that plate. Okay, because it's hot water directly from a klee rishon directly from a ben yomo and you have a ben yomo, so you don't you don't really have nat bar nat, we are meikel in a case of bedieved, but that's how the that's how the Chachmas Adam holds. That's confusing, weiter. So many technical details today.
Doesn't that kosher the fleishig pot? What what? Doesn't that kosher the fleishig pot? You have you have hot or boiling water. You don't have to kosher the fleishig pot. No. It doesn't go back up. It wouldn't go back. There's so much that I've prepared, so many things they gave here without, like, I don't know, I, you know my style by now, I don't like just reading through all the cases that they gave you because you can read those on your own, so I like to do stuff that's like inside. Okay, fine, let's skip ahead. Go to the Rav Moshe Feinstein in
source 41. Okay. Okay, can you wash all your dishes in one sink? Very, very common shaila. That l'maiseh today, Baruch Hashem, many people have the opportunity to have two sinks, but back in the day not a lot of people had two sinks, including many, many great Gedolei Hador. So the question is what to do. Let's assume for a second that the water gets yad soledes bo. If the water does
not get yad soledes bo in your sink, you're fine. It's gross, but you're fine. Okay? It doesn't get hot. The taste can only transfer if there is heat. Heat needs to be yad soledes bo. So Rav Moshe here in source 41. Okay? So we have this machlokes about hot water that is poured from a or onto a dirty either one, doesn't matter, fleishig or milchig, but from the other one. L'maiseh we are meikel. The Shach
is machmir. Says Rav Moshe Feinstein, says, ורק מהקלוח ממש says when we say that this is assur, when the Shach says that if I took a fleishig pot and I poured it onto a milchig ben yomo pot, that's where the Shach said that's assur. Says Rav Moshe, that's only where it actually spreads directly. Says והולך על שני הכלים מזה פליגי דהרמ״א אף שמן דבוק של בשר ועל
שולחן לא יאסר זה מזה the Rema is meikel. The Shach is assur, bevadai, by shemen davuk on it and the Shach is machmir. But he says l'maiseh yesh l'hachmir b'machluktam and we should be machmir להחשיב על שטח הקילוח שגם מבשל ממילא מחמת דבר באה meaning if it actually hits somewhere on that, it would be a problem. But if it doesn't hit directly, let's say you pour it in the sink and then it splashes onto the plate, that's
not direct. If it only hits a little bit of the plate, it's not spreading to everywhere else. So even though the Shach is machmir, the Shach is not as machmir as everybody might think. So if it hits the sink and then it hits everything else, then it's for sure not machmir. Why? Because that's not iruy. That's not iruy. Okay. But the question we have to discuss is the following. It's actually interesting, do we consider, if you look in source 42 in the Shemiras Shabbos, do we consider our faucets today to be a kli rishon or a kli sheini?
Well, if it's considered to be a kli sheini, that would be a huge, that would be a big heter for us because in every situation we would have it be a kli sheini. How can you consider it a kli rishon? How can you not consider it a kli rishon? What? Kli rishon is hot water. Ah, okay. So, says the Shemiras Shabbos. Is it a kli at all, the faucet? Why not? It doesn't hold anything, it's a pass through. Ah, okay. So, so then either, then it's definitely not a kli sheini, then it's for sure kli rishon. Why? No, why? At best
it's a kli sheini. Why? You just said it's not a kli. The water's, the water tank is downstairs, 100 feet away, and then it's what do you call it, it passes through the pipes. It's connected. So? Yeah. So what back to you? Why is it the same? If I, what do you call it, the hot basin of water, and I pour and I... what? Okay. Shaya, Shaya, no longer, please! Okay, it's fine, it's fine. You can say what you want to say. I'm just going to quote you the Shemiras Shabbos. I'll quote the Shemiras Shabbos and you can, Shaya.
Hold on, Shaya thinks that I'm right, which means that we're both wrong. No question that the temperature at the faucet is different than the temperature in the tank from the water, especially the longer the run is. Okay, so hold on, hold on. Says the Shemiras Shabbos, we'll see a second, we'll see the Shemiras Shabbos and the Ohr L'tzion and then we'll get to the Minchas Yitzchak about one sink. So just interesting about we're not going to spend too much time on this because it's a, it's a tangent but it's an important one. So says the Shemiras Shabbos of Neuwirth, ובנוגע
כל המים החמים היוצאים whatever comes out from your boiler, יש לחוש לגביהם ולומר שדינם כמים שבתוך כלי ראשון says the Shemiras Shabbos, it's a kli rishon. Why? Because that's where it's heated from. גם אם הם עוברים דרך צינורות ארוכים. Ah, it happens to be that it's connected, but it's still kli rishon. אם אמנם אם חם כדי שהיד סולדת בהם. So the Shemiras Shabbos and others hold that the boiler is considered your kli rishon, the faucet is your extension of that. So we could argue if the faucet should be kli sheini or not,
but the boil... The boiler is your klee rishon and it seems that if it's as long as it's hot, then everything is really just considered an extension. However, the Or L'Tzion makes a fascinating observation. The Or L'Tzion, רב ציון אבא שאול, in source 43 says that, well, this is all fine and dandy if your boiler is in your basement. But, like in many places in Eretz Yisrael where your boiler is on your roof.
Okay, so says the Tzion Abba Shaul, ולכן יש להורות דהצינור הנמצא מתחת לגג הבית כלי שני וכלי שני אינו מבשל שבכך הסבירו הסרת המים המגיעים מכלי שני וודאי מותר. Says that the boiler's on the roof, the pipes are local, for sure klee sheni and the water that comes down is only klee sheni. So רב ציון אבא שאול seems to hold that it would be different if you where it depends where your boiler is, but it seems that most most poskim hold that the boiler is your klee rishon. L'maiseh, l'maiseh, Ashkenazi
poskim hold that the faucet is just status of eerui klee rishon. We don't consider the faucet at that point as a klee sheni. Even though your your thing, your boiler is all the way 100 feet away, it's heated there, that's what's considered al gabay ha'eish. Okay, if I if I have a stovetop and I'm making soup, I have a pot of soup, that's my klee rishon. Why? 'Cause al gabay ha'eish, it's on the fire. So the boiler is on the fire. The fact that it has a lot of pipes that it has to get through to doesn't make that less than a klee sheni. What happens if you have one sink?
Okay, many many people have one sink. What do they do? What do they do? Right? Many great gedolei hador had one sink in their homes. So, one possibility is, alright, never use something that's yad soledes bo. That's solution number one. Solution number two, the Minchas Yitzchak says the following. The Minchas Yitzchak says assuming you want you want things to be hot. So says Dayan Weiss, then ideally he says וודאי ראוי להחמיר ולהדר אם אפשר לו שני בתי כליות לבשר ולחלב, you
should have two sinks. We will talk about in a second the sinks that are connected, okay, but you should have שני בתי כליות לבשר ולחלב, וכל אחד ואחד בפני עצמו, ולמי שאי אפשר לו, the person who can't do this, צריך להזהר שלא להדיח הכלים מתחילתם. So he says then really you should never do what? You should never wash either pot directly where? In the sink. רק בכלי גדול להדחה מיוחדת לבשר בפני עצמו ולחלב בפני עצמו. You should basically have some
kind of bin that you put in your sink, the bin for fleishigs and the bin for milchigs. Why? ואותו כלי הגדול לא יניחנו מתחילה רק על ידי הפסק דף או דבר. And not only that, he says when washing you should make sure that the water is going to obviously go into the bin only and not in the sink. And he says you should really raise it up a little bit. What's he concerned about? Waste of water. The sink itself is treif. The sink is treif, it has different things in it. Even if you have a a dishpan. Yeah.
That's what he's talking about. That's what he's talking about. Okay. That's the opinion of the Minchas Yitzchak that you cannot wash what one thing only. If you go to Rav Moshe on the next source, source 45, so Rav Moshe paskens like we just mentioned, that a sink only becomes basar v'chalav if you have now he's not as machmir as Dayan Weiss. Dayan Weiss is saying your sink is always treif. Rav Moshe says that's true, it's not always treif. It can only be treif if what happens at the same time? While I have in my sink, you know, ben yomo, I also poured in fleishig eerui klee
rishon all that stuff. So, you know, it has to be all these things. So says Rav Moshe, כמדומה לי שבמקום שמדיחים בסינק גופיה, right, you shouldn't really wash in the sink in the sink alone. אלא בדף מיוחד לבשר לבד ולחלב לבד. That you should rinse on on something. Why? ואף שמדיחים על חוטיי ברזל מגביהם שלא יגיעו בהסינק. And he says you don't need a bin, what should you have? What should you have? Like a rack. And
don't tell me that stuff's going to... אין שם חשש אם היה נאסר קליפת הסינק כיון שאין נוגעים. We're not as concerned. So place a rack in your sink so that the dishes don't really touch the sink itself. Okay? And and if the sink becomes really like clogged up, which is usually a shayla, that's klee sheni at that point. So again, Dayan Weiss says you gotta have a tub, Rav Moshe says you can just have a you can have a rack. Rav Belsky... Does it
make a difference what material the sink? For kashering it does, but for this it wouldn't matter. For this it wouldn't matter. So Rav Belsky in in source 46 says no, see he does not hold of racks. He sort of says a little bit against Rav Moshe Feinstein that you don't really racks don't really do enough because things are going to fall through and if those stuff starts to rise up if it gets clogged or whatever, there's potential that there's going to be an issue. So although the sink is a kli sheini and not going to forbid the
dishes if I have a little bit of residue on each dish and things are in the sink, it's going to be a problem. So really, really he says you should not rely on racks and you should get tubs like Dayan Weiss suggests. But once again, if you are Sephardi, you are in the clear. Because says Rav Ovadia in source 47, nah, you don't need a tub, you don't need a rack, just eat rice. Says Rav Ovadia המנהג כיום שנתפשט בקרב רבים לעשות במטבח שני כיורים שיהיו זה
אצל זה אחד לבשר ואחד לחלב ומכל מקום אם אירע באיזו דירה by the way, that word is not dira, okay? Because that's a dira. What's the difference? A dira is a what? A dwelling. A deira is gross. Exactly. I'll tell you later. Okay, so if you're in a- if you can't do two sinks, ומי שאין ברשותו שני כיורים נפרדים מותר להדיח כלי בשר בכיור אפילו
ברותחים says Rav Ovadia, yeah, it doesn't matter even if the sink absorbs meat flavor, ואחר כך להדיח באותו הכיור כלי חלב וגם כן ברותחים אף על פי שיש שומן it doesn't matter. It doesn't matter. Everything's going to be okay because it's only really it's not real ta'am and it's nat bar nat and all these pieces. So Rav Ovadia's the most, most meikel. So again, to recap: Sephardim, you're in the clear. Yeah. Is there a piece of that
that the dish soap makes it? Oh, we're going to get there. We're going to get there in a second. We're going to get there. We're going to get there. Again, Sephardim, can an Ashkenazi rely on Sephardi psak bedi'eved? No. What does that mean? What does that mean? In other words, bedi'eved, you didn't realize that that- not in- I would not- here's what I mean bedi'eved. Do I say that- did you do it on purpose? That's- that's not bedi'eved. That's a shogeg. So it's probably not going to treif it up because Rav Moshe doesn't think it's really treif.
Bedi'eved here means that like I- if I have one sink in my house I can't say bedi'eved I hold like Rav Ovadia. That doesn't work. It could say that if I didn't realize and I did it, I didn't have a rack, I don't have to kasher my pots and pans because Rav Moshe's not going to say that either. But you can't say that bedi'eved I hold like Rav Ovadia because we don't- that wouldn't work. Okay, next if you go to source 48, the Sefer Hakashrus. So what about you find in many homes you have a sink but it's not like a sink on either opposite ends of the kitchen, it's two sinks that are connected with
a metal piece in between. Okay, so first of all, if you have those, it is always kedai to buy a to buy like a covering and when you're washing one you should really cover the other one because things are splashing all over the place. But says the Sefer Hakashrus the following. So do we worry that things are traveling, you know, not obviously splashing over the the thing, but does the piece in the middle act as a conductor
between the two sinks? So here I am, I think I'm being frum because I have two separate sinks, and in reality I'm actually not being so frum. I mean, you're being very frum, but it's a problem. Is it- is something happening between the two sinks? So says the Sefer Hakashrus we're not so worried about that. He says, yes, lechatchila you should try to not get it. So he says הרוכש יחידת כיורים כפולה העשויה מנירוסטה. So if you have these two connecting sinks, יבחר תחילה אכן שני כיורים נפרדים לגמרי זה מזה. It's better.
It's better to get two separate. But if you can't, he says it's going to be okay. If you look here in the footnote, the reason he says that, meaning if I poured hot soup- let's just think for a second. I have a fleishig side and a milchig side. If I poured hot soup directly into my fleishig sink and I have on the other side of my sink milchig dishes, so there's a concern that that heat is just going to travel through. It's all metal. So that's what he says. Ideally it'd be better. But bedi'eved we are
not- we're not that concerned. He does say in the footnote that the reason that he's being machmir is this concept of חם מקצתו חם כולו, which means what? That if your whole sink is one entity, חם מקצתו חם כולו means what? A little bit of my sink got hot and therefore I treat the whole sink as it got hot. Well, that's a problem. Just because I call it milchig side and fleishig side, it's one sink. When you buy it from the store, you don't say \"can I have both of those sinks?\", you say \"can I have that sink that is cut into two?\". But he says
in the end lema'aseh he writes in the end of the footnote בדיעבד כשהכיור עשוי מחומר. We're pretty- we're pretty lenient about it, but it's interesting just to- you know, just to note. If it wasn't a metal sink, if it's a porcelain sink? Potentially, potentially it would- it would make an issue because then you wouldn't worry about חם מקצתו חם כולו probably because... Because once the heat goes in, whatever is in, well let's make it easy, let's say your milchig side was clogged
up and there's now water in there. Even if it's not yad soledet bo, but did some of that fleishig hatzuv that was maybe yad soledet bo now travel over and now it mixes with everything else? So he's saying we're not really so machmir about it, but there are those that are. Correct, correct. So if you look in source, okay, if you look quickly into source 49, just a little bit more on this topic before we get to some of the stuff about
sponges and soap. So lema'aseh, nobody is machmir like the Sefer Hakashrus. Even though he brings it up, nobody is machmir like the Sefer Hakashrus and he says, says Rav Moshe, he says, אם כן רוב הסינק אי אפשר לאסור כלל. Meaning, to Micah's point, even if it travels, the most it's going to assur is a teeny-teeny little bit. It's not like spreading and like creating this like monster
of a entity of treifus. The only time that iruy creates a problem is when that hot fleishig iruy, that stream comes out, it hits directly onto a ben yomo milchig thing and that little piece where it hit is assur, not that it comes and everything becomes an issue. So he says, דלא קלט אלא ממש לא יחלוק אלא חלק קטן ממנו. The only thing that's really assur is the exact area that it touched. וגם חלק הוא ספק רחוק דאם רק אם שומן של בשר. I need so many things to fall into place for this actually be an issue. Says
Rav Moshe, we are not really worried about a transfer of flavor within a sink. And he says on the other hand, נמצא שבמקום אחד משתמש אפשר להיות שם כלוך ובלוע רק מבשר ומקום אחר רק מחלב שאינו אסור. If there was some fleishig here and milchig here, they didn't mix together, there's no issue. ורוב הסינק אין בו שום בליעה. Says Rav Moshe, there's no blios here. There's no blios. Maybe
with that little spot was, that would have been an issue, but the whole sink is fine and therefore you don't have to be machmir like this shittah of the Sefer Hakashrus. Yes, Rav Moshe says you should have a rack, you don't need a tub. That's where Rav Moshe comes in. Minchas Yitzchak and Rav Bielsky says you need a tub. Rav Moshe holds you don't need a tub, but you also don't need to be machmir like this shittah of the Sefer Hakashrus. And one more, if you look in source 50, ספר כל בני ביתך כהלכה. No, he is not ruling Rav Ovadia. No,
he is not ruling like Rav Ovadia. Eddie, you really want this Rav Ovadia. Eddie, I give you a blessing, go for it. Okay, so if you look in source 50, he says, this is a, it's a great line here. First of all, he quotes the תשובות הגאון אב בית דין דעברעצין. That is the shittah of the Be'er Moshe. The Be'er Moshe was known as the Debretziner Rav. There were, I believe, five brothers.
Five brothers. They were mamash iluyim. The Debretziner is one of them. He was an av beis din in Debretzin and then he came to America. He argues with Rav Moshe a bunch of times. There's a very famous teshuvah, I think where he argues with Rav Moshe about yarmulkes. Wearing a yarmulke in the workplace, I think is where he argues with Rav Moshe. He quotes Rav Moshe a lot of times, Rav Moshe never quotes him. So, but he quotes the Debretziner Rav that sinks are two separate
sinks because there is a space in between and he says, יש קונים שני סינקים עשוים מחתיכה אחת והיינו שני סינקים שחתוכים מחתיכה אחת שיש שתי גומות באחת מדיחים כלי בשר ובאחת כלי חלב זה נכון. Can I do that? Can I buy this kind of sink? אף דדומה דמשתמש בכלי גדול חציו לבשר וחציו לחלב. Or does it look more like I bought a big pot and I just use half of it for milchig and half of it for meat. ודאי אי אפשר לומר שהסינק כלי גדול. Don't, what are you talking about? כי אבר מפסיק בין
שני הסינקים ואין שום הוה אמינא. There is no thought in the world של בלוע ילך מצד אחד לצד השני. Stop talking about this. ואין כדאי לחפש חומרות כגון זה. Stop looking for chumros. Says the Be'er Moshe, your sink is fine, the double sink is fine. What? Don't be so frum. Yeah, don't be so frum. Meaning, if there's a real, that by the way, this also shows you what a chumrah is. If there's no basis, okay, the Sefer Hakashrus says it, Rav Moshe doesn't hold
like it, the Debretziner doesn't hold like it, there's not a basis for it. Okay, so it's not a chumrah. If you have basis for things, then you have a chumrah. If you don't have basis for things, you don't have a chumrah. Okay, so lema'aseh, that is how we pasken. Fine. Last one here in source fifty-one. So again, if I, if I either have one sink or maybe I accidentally washed in, you know, Milchig dairy and Fleishig dishes together, right? I, I
was washing off my Milchig plate then I was washing off my Fleishig plate, I didn't realize what happened. So number one I should be okay because let's assume it's not yad soledet bo. Okay because most likely you're not, if you're hand-washing dishes, you're most likely not hand-washing dishes in yad soledet bo. If you are, then it's not yad soledet bo because if your hand isn't recoiling, then that would be yad soledet bo. That's number one. Number two, maybe we can hold that the faucet is kli sheini, so we're gonna be okay. Number two. Number three, even if it's an irui kli rishon, the Rema says we're,
we're meikel even though the Shach is machmir. And we learned, and we're gonna talk about soap in a second and then you get to Rav Moshe in source fifty-one. So says Rav Moshe, he says even if, even if you hold that the faucet is a kli rishon, when you turn your hot faucet on what comes out first? Cold water. So says Rav Moshe, that makes it anything that comes out after that a kli sheini. The chidush of Rav Moshe, that when you place hot water, he says וגם ראוי אני
קל וחומר אם מצד צינון הדפנות לבד הכלי שני נתקרר. The whole point of a kli sheini is that the taste, the walls, the Tosafot in Shabbos says that dafnos mehammos, it keeps it hot, and a kli... if you make tea you'll notice that your tea also cooks in a kli shelishi. So why are we okay with it? Because dafnos mekareros. It's, it's already weakened. Now there are those that don't make tea because of this shaileh, this bizman they make tea essence
before Shabbos. So but says Rav Moshe, if you also open the cold water, the water leaving the faucet is a kli sheini and therefore everything after that is really not going to be an issue and therefore no matter what we seem to really, really be okay if whatever I used. Okay. How about tankless water heaters? But we will not discuss that now, but it's a great shaileh. It wouldn't impact anything about this but... would it go straight to a kli sheini? No, why? The water is still
cold. Water still cold. Yeah, no matter. It just heats it up fast but it doesn't change what's already in the pipes. Right. It's horizontal inside it comes out. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, obviously, that'll be different. That'll be different. Okay. So if you look in the Sefer Ohel Yaakov, he says the following: separate sponges. Right, many, many times a shaileh is asked is oh my gosh I used the wrong sponge. The הלכה למשה מסיני is blue is Milchig and red, pink is Fleishig. Okay,
that is what you should be doing. So says the Sefer Ohel Yaakov the following: What happens if I use the wrong sponge? ובזמן שרוחצים הכלים צריכים לזכור לייחד ספוג אחד לבשר ואחד לחלב ואחד לפרווה. You need three. ומי שלובש כפפות בשעת הרחיצה יהיה לו אחד לבשר ואחד לחלב. Fine. We agree. Says, u-ve-chol makom in the footnote, יש להקל כמעט בכל מקרה.
Almost every single time a shaileh is asked, Rabbi I washed it with the wrong sponge, the Rabbi is going to say it's fine. Why? Says the following: Number one, דאינו רגילות בבתינו לשטוף כלים בחום כזה. Number one, you better not be using that hot water. Okay. Number two, אם נניח שהמים חמים, fine, Rabbi, it was, I love boiling water, my hands were burning but it was hot. עד שהיד סולדת בו אפשר להתיר שמסתמא לא דבוק על הספוג לכלוך בעין.
Says even if it's yad soledet bo, the sponge was clean. It wasn't, I can't imagine your sponge had like you're washing your ben yomo mac and cheese pot. Mac and cheese and you took the Fleishig sponge accidentally. Even if it was yad soledet bo, are you telling me there was pieces of meatballs like still stuck in the sponge? Can't be. Fine. And then he says, you know what? Fine, let's keep going. ואם תמצא לומר, no no Rabbi, it was boiling hot, I,
I put the meatballs on to start because I wanted to ask the shaileh, נתבטל בשישים במים ששוטף בהם. How, you didn't have massive amounts of meatballs on your sponge, you had a little bit of dirt and a ton of water, you have shishim. He says, no Rabbi, no, no, no, no. It was burning hot and I put meatballs in and I used a little bit of water. אפשר לומר דהסבון פוגם המאכל בעין שעליו. At the end of the day, I would hope that you are washing with soap.
Now, le-chatchila you can't rely on this, you can't le-chatchila say just use soap for everything but that's why usually when the shaileh comes, I found my Fleishig knife in my Milchig dishwasher. You have an issue of be'ain because unless you're a neurotic person, I imagine that something was left, depends on how you wash your dishes or how you load the dishwasher, it's totally up
to you, but I imagine most people there's a little bit of stuff left on. So now I have the be'ain issue. Okay, but at least I had, and I might not have had shishim, depends on how much be'ain I have versus how much water comes out. So that's a big problem with dishwashers. The only thing left is soap. Okay, so I used soap. So a person used soap, it's nosein taam l'fgam and therefore your it's going to be okay and therefore if you find in your fleishig drawer there's something else, we usually have what's called a sfek sfeika. Meaning, sfek number one is whether they even washed together.
And even if they washed together, maybe it wasn't even ben yomo and it's really sfek sfeika sfeika and even if it was ben yomo, there's other things involved. So almost all the time that you call the rav and you say I found, I washed the wrong sponge, I had the wrong dish, or I found the wrong dishwasher, we're meikel almost all the time because you're always going to have one of these issues saving the day. Okay, we're going to hold it here and then pick up next week with the topic of nosein taam l'fgam. There will be a lot in the notes that we did not cover tonight because there's a lot of just some applications of the rema that are just, you
can read on your own, so print out before shabbos or yom tov.